# 大家好 現在的酸棗(南酸棗)都熟了哦
Hi everyone! The hog plums are ripe now.
# 我去山上撿點酸棗 但是這個刀有點鈍啦 要磿利一點
Let me go to the hill and pick some hog plums. But this knife is a bit blunt. I gotta sharpen it.
# 因為現在酸棗剛成熟 山上那個草
Cuz now the plums are just ripe. And the weeds on the hill,
# 都已經太長啦 所以我要拿這個刀把它劈掉
are already too long. So I’m cutting them off with this knife.
# 不劈掉的話會割腳的哦
Otherwise they may cut my legs.
# 你看 長褲又沒得穿 穿了條短褲
Look! I don’t even have trousers. I’m just wearing pants.
# 好啦 不用磿啦 這個刀已經很利了 本來就很利的
Alright! I think it enough. It is already very sharp. It’s always very sharp.
# 你看 路過兄弟家的板栗樹哦 這個
Look! We pass by my buddy’s chestnut tree. Here.
# 很多的 他家的板栗又大 又大個 又多籽
Here are a lot. His chestnuts are big and, big and, there are plenty of nuts.
# 我去看一下有沒有先
Let me go and see if there are any.
# 檢兩個來吃一下也好
It would be nice if I could pick a couple of them.
# 你看 這裡就有一個哦 那麼大的 又大又黃
Look! Right here is one. It’s so big, big and brown,
# 又大又紅的
I mean big and red.
# 才檢了一個 太少啦
I've picked just one. It’s too few.
# 你看 樹上還有好多爆的哦 都裂開啦 它就是不掉下來
Look! Many in the tree have already cracked, cracked open. But they’re not falling down.
# 太氣人啦
It’s too bad.
# 哎 掉啦
Ay! It drops.
# 終於到了這個 lian ma gai (南酸棗)的樹下
Finally, we’re under the hog plum tree.
# 你看 這個lian ma gai (南酸棗)
Have a look at these hog plums.
# 一樹都是青的 還沒掉下來哦
The green ones are all over the tree, and they’re not falling down.
# 它從這掉了一點點下來
Some of them have fallen down here along the slope.
# 熟了它就會掉下來 不熟的它不掉的
They fall when they’re ripe. The green ones never fall.
# 哎呀 這兩個
Aya! These two…
# 這個 壞啦 這個
This one, is rotten, this one.
# 這裡多哦 這裡 剛好掉在這裡 這坑上
Here are a lot! Here, they landed right here, right on this pit.
# 你看這個是 爛的 不要
Look! This is, rotten. Pass.
# 我們要檢要檢好的
We pick only the good ones.
# 你看這個 酸棗就這樣子的 它裡面的肉
Have a look at this one. This is how a hog plum looks like, how the pulp inside looks like.
# 嗯~吃酸棗的時候第一口是甜的
Um~ The first bite of hog plum is always sweet.
# 慢慢的就越來越酸 越來越酸
But the sweetness is gradually overtaken by the sourness.
# 好像裡面的汁是甜的 但是果肉就是慢慢的越來越酸啦
It seems that the juice is sweet. But the sourness from the pulp gradually comes in.
# 檢了半個小時就搞了那麼一點點
So I’ve picked just a tiny little bit here in half an hour.
# 等一下 我去兄弟家 他家樹底下應該多一點
Later, let me go to my buddy’s place. There should be more under his tree.
# 我要檢一點回來 我們這 這是我家的樹哦
Let me pick some from his place. Mine here... This is my tree, you know.
# 不掉的 全在樹上你看到沒有 好多都是青的
They don’t fall. They're all still in the tree, most are still green.
# 它們沒掉下來 兄弟家的掉下來 去撿兄弟家的
They don’t fall. My buddy’s plums do fall. Let me pick his plums.
# 好啦 回去準備一下 做酸棗糕
Alright! Let's go back, and get ready, to make some hog plum strips.
# 第二天
The second day
# 這個酸棗撿回來啦
So we’ve taken the hog plums back.
# 要用開水煮一下
They need to be blanched in water first.
# 煮一下就可以把那個皮直接剝掉就可以啦
After blanching them, they can be, can be peeled right away.
# 滿滿的一鍋
One whole, full pot
# 你看 開始慢慢開裂啦
Look! They’re cracking open now, slowly.
# 這個要煮熟啦
It’s done now.
# 像這個要用那個水沖一下啊
It’s like, they need to be rinsed for a while.
# 好啦 洗乾淨啦 要把它全部捏碎來
Alright! It’s clean now. I need to smash them all.
# 你看 這個酸棗就這橏把它捏出來的哦 這個
Look! The hog plums need to be squeezed out, you know. Squeeze like this.
# 一擠就擠出來啦
A single squeeze is enough.
# 你看 快裝不下啦
Look! It can’t take anymore.
# 但是也快沒啦 就那麼一丟丟啦
But we are done anyway. Just a tiny little bit remains.
# 這個要攪拌一下 把那個籽要把它去掉
It needs to be stirred, so as to remove the seeds.
# 這個酸棗把它做了自己吃的哦
The hog plums strips are for ourselves only.
# 就沒那麼講究 本來買了那個一次性手套的
So it's not so delicate. In fact I’ve already ordered disposable gloves.
# 資還沒到 但是我急著想吃
The delivery has not yet arrived. But I’m craving for the strips.
# 就先做了
So I’m making it now.
# 你看 越搓它越漂亮
Look! Kneading it makes it look prettier.
# 啊 看這個
Ah! Have a look at this one.
# 還要繼續搓
I still need to keep kneading it.
# 這是純手工的哦
It’s hundred percentage handmade, you know,
# 沒有任何添加
without any additives.
# 你看 這個就有點像豬油一樣
Look! It now looks a little bit like lard.
# 這全是果肉哦 就把果肉把取出來了
This is all pulp. The pulp is now extracted.
# 然後我給你放南瓜 下給它拌一下
Then I’ll put some pumpkin, and mix with it.
# 因為這個太少啦
Cuz it’s too little here.
# 不夠吃的
It’s not enough.
# 就這樣一點樹枝樹葉沒事的 樹枝樹葉也可以吃
Here are some branches and leaves. No worries. They cause no harms.
# 那個酸棗太少啦 我摘個攀蒲來湊一下
There are too few hog plums. I’m gonna pick a pumpkin to make up the portion.
# 湊一下就多 肉多一點嘛
So that we have more, something more to eat.
# 不然不夠吃啊
It’s not enough otherwise.
# 剛好一個攀蒲
A pumpkin is right here.
# 哎呀 這把刀
Aya! This knife.
# 你看 剛剛好啊 這個小攀蒲
Look! It’s perfect, this little pumpkin.
# 全部削進去一蒸它就可以啦
Cut the whole thing into pieces, steam it, and it’s done.
# 這是老攀蒲哦
This is an old pumpkin.
# 雖然個子小 但是它很老
Though it’s small, it’s very old.
# 要把它劈開哦 把裡面的籽去掉
I gotta cut it open, and take away all the seeds inside.
# 你看 裡面的籽要把它拿掉
Look! The seeds inside need to be taken away.
# 不拿掉的話就會有籽
There would be seeds otherwise.
# 切小片一點
Let me cut it into smaller pieces.
# 好啦 等下我就洗乾淨
Alright! I’ll wash it in a while,
# 就用那個 鍋蒸一下 把它蒸熟了之後
and then you know, steam it in the cooker. After steaming it,
# 就跟那個酸棗榚的那個
I’ll mix it with the, you know,
# (就跟那個 酸棗糕的) [SIC] 那個囊
the dough, of the hog plum strips.
# 一起攪拌一下
Mix them all together.
# 好啦 放鍋里面蒸
Alright! Steam it in the cooker.
# 把這個攀蒲
The pumpkin,
# 像這樣放就可以了
simply put it here.
# 把它蒸熟來
Steam it until it becomes soft.
# 好 還有一點 給你來煮一下
Alright! Here’s still a bit. Cook it as well.
# 哇 熟啦熟啦
Wa! It’s done it’s done!
# 來 把這個攀蒲搞下去 直接這樣放下去
C’mon! Let me put in the pumpkin. Just put it in right away.
# 全部都已經爛啦 已經煮爛啦
It’s already smashed. It has already been softened.
# 加點糖 來 全部一拱 拱下來
Put some sugar. C’mon! Pour it in, everything.
# 搞多點糖 甜一點更好
We need a bit more sugar, the sweeter the better.
# 你看 加點葡萄糖 這是攝影小哥兒子吃的葡萄糖
Look! Put some glucose powder. This is taken from Mr. Cameraman’s son.
# 多搞點
Put more.
# 到時候我填一點給他
I’ll refill it for him.
# 好啦好啦 可以
Alright, alright. Okay!
# 這樣可以了
It's alright now.
# 夠靚
Beautiful, isn’t it?
# 還是 繼續攪拌
Then, keep on stirring.
# 你看 先吃一點
Look! Let me try a bit first.
# 嗯 可以哦
Um! Not bad.
# 酸酸甜甜的 曬乾了更好吃
Sweet and sour. It would taste even better when it’s dried.
# 可以 哇 直的可以哦 很不錯
Not bad! Wa! It’s really nice. Really not bad.
# 那種
It’s like,
# 又有酸味又有甜味又有南瓜味
sweetness and sourness, combined with the taste of pumpkins,
# 還有那個lian ma gai (南酸棗)的味道
and also the, the taste of hog plums.
# 好啦 準備烤它
Alright! Let’s bake it.
# 這種天氣 本來要曬的
This weather… It should be dried under the sun, in fact.
# 沒辦法曬 只能烤了
But it’s now impossible. We can only bake it.
# 哇 這樣差不多可以啦 讓它慢慢這樣子烤
Alright! It’s almost done. Bake it here, slowly.
# 你看 現在越來越漂亮啦
Look! It's becoming prettier every second.
# 黃黃的
Golden brown
# 上面都已經乾啦
The surface is already dried.
# 還要再烤一下
But it still needs to be baked for a while.
# 你看 可以吃了哦
Look! It’s alright now.
# 嗯~太好吃啦 因為還沒乾 再烤一下才行
Um~ Delicious! It still needs to be baked, cuz it’s still not completely dried.
# 因為天色已晚
I mean, cuz it’s late now.
# 酸棗糕就這樣做的
That’s how hog plum strips are made.
# 要吃把它切成一條一條 要烤很久的
It needs to be cut into stripes before they can be eaten. It needs to be baked for a very long time.
# 第三次
The third day
# 昨天沒烤乾 今天烤了一天才把它烤乾
We couldn't completely dry it yesterday. We've been baking it for a whole day today before it becomes dry.
# 我要把它切到來
So I’m now cutting it up.
# 切這個的時候要放點那個葡萄糖粉
I need some, some glucose powder when I’m cutting it.
# 把它抺一下 這樣就不會粘
Spray it here. So that the dough won’t stick.
# 你看 首先切一小塊
Look! I cut a small piece first.
# 這樣 再把它們抺上葡萄糖
And then, spray some glucose powder on it.
# 抺上葡萄糖其實就是沒那麼粘啦
In fact that’s to prevent it from being too sticky.
# 你看 現在就好多啦 這樣
Look! It’s so much better now.
# 再搞一點葡萄糖
Put some more glucose powder.
# 這樣 撈一下 撈一下 就這是一條一條啦
Then, stir them, stir them and now they they’re stripes.
# 你看 這就是酸棗糕 切的時候還沒 還不是很乾
Look! These are hog plum strips. It was not, not really that dry when I was cutting it.
# 要再烤乾一些 你看
It should have been baked a bit longer, look!
# 嗯~可以哦
Um! Not bad.
# 真的 很不錯
Seriously, really nice.
# 這就是 酸棗糕
This is called, hog plum strip.
# 你看 這個一條一條的可以把它裝到罐子裡面去
Look! These stripes can be put into a jar.
# 到時候想吃的時候就拿幾個來吃
We can just take some whenever we want them.
# 到時候有粉絲來了就可以給他(她)們吃
Or we can serve our fans when they visit us.
# 很好吃的這個
It’s really tasty, you know.
# 如果烤乾一點的話就很好
It would be even better if they’re baked longer.
# 那個 就會火 火燒啦 本來用太陽曬最好的
I mean, it would be burnt however. The best is drying under the sun, in fact.
# 你看 很溧亮了吧 有點像了哦
Look! It’s pretty, isn’t it? It looks the authentic ones.
# 放在這裡吃就可以啦 幾天就把它吃完啦
Just leave it here, it’s fine. They will be gone in a few days.
# 好啦 今天的視頻就到這裡啦
Alright! The video ends here.
# 這罐小罐的就送給攝影小哥吃
This small jar is for Mr. Cameraman.